用罗马人的血把他妈的雪地染红
We shall see roman blood upon fucking snow!
我绝不会带着他们去送死
I will not march my people to the afterlife.
我也绝不会让罗马狗从背后捅刀子
And I will not die with a roman sword in my back.
我警告过你 远离我这种人
I have warned you to stay far from men of my kind.
你经历了痛苦和失去
You have known pain and loss.
和我们当中的很多人一样
A misfortune shared by many among us.
到时你听提比略命令
Fall to command beneath Tiberius.
怎么要剑都拿不稳的小子担此大任
Not a boy prone to losing his sword.
瞧瞧 你又该卑躬屈膝了
Here we stand, you beneath heel.
- 我要留在希留爱沙 - 就在这座宅子里
- I am to remain in Sinuessa? - In this very villa.
- 服侍提比略 - 我知道他很看重你
- Beneath Tiberius. - I know how much he cares for you.
她非常急切地要与你父亲谈话
She was desperate to break word with your father.
她有何事如此急迫
What concerns so move her?
那就是他们的秘密了
Ah, that is the mystery.
我的奴隶送回希留爱沙了吗
Was my slave escorted back to Sinuessa?
她跑到叛贼的队伍里了
She has moved to join the rebellion.
叛贼突破了围墙
The rebels have breached the wall.
我们必须撤退
We must fall back!
伟大的克拉苏在我们面前屁滚尿流地跑了
The mighty Crassus flees from us!
他会回来的
He will return.
《斯巴达克斯：诅咒者之战》
《分道扬镳》
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
罗马人又从后方打过来了
Romans set again upon rear position!
克雷斯
Crixus!
罗马今天就派这么点人来
Is that all Rome has to offer this day?!
我还没杀够呢
I have not yet had my fill of blood!
克拉苏一天之内就进攻了两次
Crassus lays assault twice upon a day.
可每次兵力都不多
Yet with but a handful of men.
他要拖慢我们的脚步 好让大军追上来
He seeks but time for his legions to narrow gap between us,
他知道我们要保护老弱病残 必然放慢脚步
knowing we will slow to protect those weakest among us.
这一招他是用定了
A strategy taking firmest hold.
告诉你的神 我克雷斯鄙视他们
Tell your gods that Crixus pisses upon them.
克雷斯
Crixus.
趁这家伙还活着 我要问他点事
I would break words while he is yet of this world.
克拉苏还有几天时间赶上我们
How many days march does Crassus find himself to our backs?
吃屎去吧 该死的奴隶
Stroke cock, you fucking slave!
让他配合一点
See his tongue made more agreeable.
四天
Four days!
Four days.
饶命
Please.
拿好武器 继续行进
Gather weapons, and rejoin march.
我回答了你的问题
I gave what was asked!
求求你 留我一条命吧
I beg of you, spare my life!
你求错人了
You beg the wrong man.
根据腐烂程度和气味 已经死了三天了
Gone to grass three days past, by rot and stench.
我们离斯巴达克斯又近了一天的路程
We gained another day on Spartacus.
- 停下 - 这有什么奇怪的
- Halt! - Is it a wonder?
从米利亚峰一路过来 我们几乎没休息过
The men have barely rested since Melia Ridge.
今晚也不能休息
Nor will they find such this night.
命令第二军团停止休息
Give command to second legion to fall from rest,
不必等全体集合 即刻开始追击
and continue pursuit in advance of fullest number.
你催得太厉害了
You push them too hard.
现在不是心慈手软的时候
Now is not the time for gentle words nor soft intent.
我是为了将来的战事着想
I harden towards future conflict.
处在崩溃边缘的军队
Yet a legion on the brink of collapse
怎么对抗斯巴达克斯和他的队伍
is ill thought towards Spartacus and his army.
跟不上行进速度的人
Any within ranks unable to keep pace
直接原地处死
shall be struck down where they stand.
十一抽杀律难道还不够…
Was decimation not threat enough
我绝不能让他从我手心里溜走
I will not let him slip from fucking grasp!
统帅
Imperator.
梅泰勒斯元老求见
Senator Metellus demands audience.
梅泰勒斯
Metellus?
你要我去罗马传达消息
You dispatch me to Rome to crow
说斯巴达克斯必败于米利亚峰
of the inevitable fall of Spartacus upon Melia Ridge,
结果让我丢尽了脸面
only to have recent news brand me overreaching fool!
我不喜欢你说话的腔调
I find your tone displeasing.
我也不喜欢打败了仗所造成的影响
As I find of many things swirling about failed campaign.
斯巴达克斯只是延迟了死期
Spartacus but prolongs his end.
回罗马传信吧
Return to Rome and deliver message.
我是共和国的元老
I am a Senator of the Republic!
不是你他妈的信使
Not fucking message boy to deliver
传达连影子都看不到的捷报
yet more tidings of imagined victories.
我说你是你就是
You stand what I deem necessary.
难道你忘了我们的交易
Or has our arrangement slipped from mind?
去你的希留爱沙宅子
Keep promise of villa in Sinuessa
去你的花不完的税金
and purse lined with the coin of taxes!
跟克拉苏的名号搅在一起
Association with the name of Crassus
只会玷污我自己的名声
will only serve to further taint my own.
一切都不会改变
Nothing has fallen to change.
我会彻底剿灭斯巴达克斯及其走狗
I shall grind Spartacus and his rebellion beneath heel,
正如我承诺的那样
as I have promised.
挺有志气的嘛 据说你最心爱的奴隶
Lofty words coming from a man whose most trusted slave
跑去投靠了叛贼头子…
is said to have fled to join the rebel king
我们别掺和
Stay from argument.
你他妈的疯了
You have lost fucking mind!
你竟敢对我动手
I will see the Senate cast you out
元老院必定将你扫地出门…
for laying hands upon honored member
你
You…
他妈的
will do…
按我
as I…
命令的
fucking…
去做
command!
马科斯
Marcus.
回罗马去
Return to Rome.
敢提这件事 敢说我一句坏话
Speak of this, or any word against me…
我就是倾家荡产 也要找个晚上做了你
and I shall devote fortune towards your death in darkness of night.
送他上马
See him upon his horse.
第二军团即刻追击斯巴达克斯
And second legion set to purpose towards Spartacus.
传令下去 全军待命 准备转移
Give word to stand ready to move upon a moment's notice.
我们不可因一时安逸而掉以轻心
We must not fall to sense of comfort.
我可不想学那惊弓之鸟
I do not favor fleeing like rabbits
猎人没来就四处逃窜
at imagined footfall of hunter.
我也是
Nor I.
但我们在重整兵力之前
Yet we must stay in advance of Crassus
- 还是得避开克拉苏的锋芒 - 很明智
- until numbers are replenished. - A wise path.
虽然我更喜欢把罗马军杀个片甲不留
Though one paved with Roman heads fucking preferred.
如果我们大意了 片甲不留的只会是我们
We shall find our own upon it, if we fall from caution.
我还是第一次听你说这种话
A word once unfamiliar upon your tongue.
我是替那些老弱病残着想
Spoken now with thought towards those less able among us.
而他们和战士消耗的粮食同样多
And yet they devour as much as any man of sword or spear.
他说得没错
He is not wrong in this.
粮草将尽
Supplies are nearly spent.
我们很快又要饿着肚子 举步维艰
Soon hunger will again be upon us, weighing each step.
甘尼克斯
Gannicus.
派卢戈他们去前方侦察
Gather Lugo and scout ahead.
看看有什么机会能抢些粮草回来
I would know of any opportunity towards grain or meat.
我们不可能永远避开他们
We cannot run for an eternity.
我们迟早要跟他们决一死战
One day soon we will once again have to stand and fight.
迟早的
One day.
你知道他这么做是对的
You know he holds right in this.
战争时期 没有什么是确定无疑的
No ground held is certain, in times of war.
有可能吗
Is it possible?
再次从克拉苏的血口中逃脱
To slip from jaws of Crassus yet again?
我不会让你落入虎口的
I will not see you caught between them.
我收集来的柴火挺多的
I have been overreaching in my efforts,
一起生火吧
and would share.
如果你也同意
If you are of a mind…?
操
Fuck!
生火吧
See fire to life.
别忘了我盯着你
And know my eyes are upon you.
他看我的眼神里还是有敌意
His stare yet holds the promise of violence.
那就继续杀罗马人 证明你自己
Continue to prove yourself against the Romans,
化敌为友
and see it soften.
他完全不用在这方面担心什么
The man need not fall to worry in such regard.
不过说到我心中所属
Yet in matters nearer the heart,
他倒是有必要担忧的
his concerns are well founded.
不要再想这种事
Rid yourself of them.
也不要再说这种话了
And break no more upon subject.
如果你毫不在乎 一笑而过
If you had laughed carelessly at my words,
那便是我自作多情了
I would have known feelings misplaced.
可你极力掩饰
Yet you froth and foam,
反倒说明你有所心动
showing they strike reflective chord.
是你自己会错意了
You mistake reflection for your own.
我走过时发现你偷看我 莫非也是我弄错了
And do I mistake your eyes stealing glance as I pass?
还有我走近时 你那么急促的呼吸
Or breath from lips catching when I draw near?
我害怕要露天席地而睡
I had feared night spent beneath open sky.
谢谢你
Gratitude.
- 不算什么 - 不算什么
- A thing of little note. - Little?
你把快乐建立在我的痛苦之上可没过多久
It was but short time past you would have found joy in my suffering.
你别以为我已经忘了
Do not think me so far removed from thought.
那你为什么要帮我
Then why offer hand?
我只是在帮斯巴达克斯
I offer it towards Spartacus.
我是搞不懂
It baffles fucking sense,
不过他似乎对你有些着迷
yet he appears to carry affection towards you.
我 我不知道说什么
I-I've have not the words
我也不想听到
Nor I desire to hear them.
斯巴达克斯这辈子牺牲得够多了
Spartacus has sacrificed much in this life.
他应该享受一点点快乐
He deserves some small measure of happiness in return.
很多人也是如此
As so many are owed.
抱歉
Apologies.
我需要帮助
I am in need of aid.
你要用力
You must bear down.
用尽全力
As hard as you are able.
- 再来 - 我做不到
- Again. - I cannot.
冷静
Calm yourself.
按她说的做
And do as instructed.
携雨之使者
The Bringer of Rain…
如果你想活下去 就用力生下来 快
If you wish to live, bear down. Now.
快给我把刀子
Blade. Quickly.
你喜得贵子
You are blessed with a son.
看这孩子的小弟弟
Look at the cock on this one,
晃来晃去的多威风
dangling as if from Jupiter himself!
但愿他懂得尊重别人的意愿
I pray he uses it only upon the willing.
他真是幸运 有这么熟练的双手
He is fortunate to have such skilled hands
带他来到世间
to bring him into this world.
你之前也接生过吗
You have done this before?
做过很多次 给我主人的女奴隶
Many times, for those owned by my dominus.
不知道我是否认识他
I wonder if I might have known of him.
他叫什么
What name did he carry?
庞波
Pompo.
坎帕尼亚附近的一个畜牧主
A raiser of low animals near Campania
她说庞波
She speaks of Pompo.
但手上的印记却显示另有其主
Yet mark upon her arm tells of a different master…
你是马科斯•克拉苏的奴隶
You were slave to Marcus Crassus himself?
以前是
I was.
又来一个卧底
Another spy, sent to infiltrate rank.
什么卧底愿意暴露身份给孩子接生
What manner of spy pauses in deceit to give aid in child's birth?
那家伙派卧底来就是要我们的命
One sent by the man trying to end our fucking lives!
他并没有派我来
He did not send me.
我是从他在米利亚峰的大帐里逃出来的
I fled his tent upon the Melia Ridge.
你为何要背叛他 莫非喜欢这严寒暴雪
Why did you turn from him, in favor of cold and storm?
快说
Break word.
不然以后休想还能说话
Or find yourself forever unable.
这姑娘和你们很多人一样 都是逃亡至此
The girl is fugitivus as many among you,
你管她是从哪个主人那里逃出来的
regardless of which dominus she fled.
她需要保护
She deserves protection,
而不是半遮半掩的威胁
not veiled threats.
我从不半遮半掩
I hide behind no veils.
带有敌人印记的人也不能隐瞒不答
Nor shall any bearing mark of my enemy.
克拉苏待我不薄
Crassus himself has seen no harm to me.
但他儿子深深地伤害了我
Yet name of honored son inflicted grievous injury.
而且还不肯善罢干休
And would have continued to do so.
我妻子也有过这般遭遇
My wife stood equally mistreated,
也是拜她所谓的主人所赐
by those that called themselves her masters.
你来照看她
She's your responsibility.
给她吃喝
See her provided for.
如果她所说有半句虚言
And know if her tale falls from truth,
她的死期也就不远了
then her life shall swiftly follow.
感谢
Gratitude.
我有顾虑
I hold concern in this.
莱塔说的没错
Laeta breaks truth in the matter.
我们不能拒绝任何渴望自由的奴隶
We cannot turn from any slave wishing freedom.
她自由了 终于可以和我们一起挨饿了
Then let her be free to starve with the rest of us.
今晚睡前把一切准备就绪
See all readied before you take sleep.
天一亮我们就跟上第二军团出发
We follow second legion at first light.
我好像没有叫你过来
I do not recall commanding your presence.
最近的事容不得我不来
Recent events spur initiative.
出去吧
Fall from sight.
我担心的是
I am of a concern.
你的父亲
Towards your father.
你有什么想法
What are the lay of your thoughts?
不少
Fitful.
自从米利亚峰进展不顺 他就…
His manner since Melia Ridge has been…
不太对劲
unsettling.
他是个铁腕领袖
He but commands with firm hand.
痛揍自己的盟友
Clenched into fist striking ally.
梅泰勒斯口不择言
Metellus spoke out of turn.
没错 他是个不折不扣的蠢货
He is a fool, you will find no argument.
但同时还是共和国元老院的人
Yet one that stands a fucking Senator of the Republic.
我父亲也是
As does my father.
但他的反应已经失去了理智
Whose reply far outweighed balance of insult.
而他一向对自控能力
Especially for a man who prides himself
特别有信心
on appearance of control.
我们在打仗 提比略
We are at war, Tiberius.
哪怕只有一点点失策
Against an enemy that will exploit
敌人摸到了
even the slightest weakness,
必然要我们万劫不复
and bring us all to our doom.
你有话直说 不要拐弯抹角
Tread path of more direct route, and arrive at point.
你再次获得了你父亲的信任
Beloved son has regained favor of his father.
从你嘴里提出的建议
Measured counsel spilling from your mouth
或许能让他恢复理智
may yet again fill him with reason.
驱散克芮的背叛带给他的痛苦
And dispel troubled thought of Kore escaping
你他妈的是为了你自己
The fucking cock between your legs!
才来这里的吧
That is why you have come to me.
想要平息他的怒火
To calm storm of his wrath before
以免扫地出门
you are swept away in downpour.
你误会了
You mistake intent
难道不是你违抗命令
Were you not the one who defied command
带克芮去米利亚峰的
to spirit Kore to Melia Ridge?
为她的背叛大开方便之门
Giving her opportunity to betray him?
她是流着泪来求我的
She pleaded with tears upon cheek,
要跟你父亲谈谈他的混蛋儿子
to break words with your father about his fucking son.
略施小计
A simple ruse,
为她逃离米利亚峰 投靠叛贼
one imagined to make escape upon Melia Ridge
找个借口而已
to join the rebels.
我相信其中确有把戏
Oh I believe there to be ruse.
但不是深受宠爱的奴隶所玩的把戏
Yet not one formed by mind of loving slave.
你对她干了什么 小子
What did you do to her, boy,
逼她逃跑
to make her flee?
是不是用你那发育不全的小弟弟
Did you force that tiny cock inside her
你太过分了 护民官
You fucking overstep, Tribune!
我每天都冒犯你
Many times each day.
不过这件事 你我都知道是事实
Yet in this, we both know I do not.
等我揭露了你的兽行
I will uncover the truth of what you have done.
你父亲便能恢复理智了
And your father will fall again to reason…
知道背叛他的人并不是克芮
when wounded heart is balmed by knowledge
这对他受伤的心是多么安慰啊
that Kore is not the one who has betrayed him.
这孩子降临在如此残酷的世界
The child is born into a life of piss and shit.
他是自由的
He is free.
和我们一样
As so many among us.
因为你 我也有了自由
As I stand now, because of you.
我希望你得到的不仅仅是自由两个字
I wish you blessed with more than just a word.
还有锦衣玉食
An endless bounty of food.
和一个为你遮风挡雨的家
And a proper home to keep you warm on coldest night.
或许还能养育一个我们的孩子
Perhaps even a child of our own upon a day…
但我现在没有能力给你这一切
Yet I have not had the strength to provide you with any of this.
是你把我从矿场中解救出来
Your strength saw me from the mines.
指引我走出黑暗 重新找回自我
Guided me from the shadows, returning life to faded shell.
却给了你血肉横飞 刀光剑影的生活
A life stained with blood and battle.
这是我自己的选择
My path has been chosen.
不是命运的选择
Not by the fates.
也不是神灵的选择
Not by the gods themselves.
我选择了站在你身边
I choose to walk by your side,
无论今生还是来世
in this life and the one that follows.
在我们走到生命尽头之前
Until we find ourselves upon its shores…
我只希望多杀几个罗马人
I desire only to send more fucking Romans there before us.
有你是我莫大的荣幸
I do not deserve a woman such as you.
这是只属于你一个人的荣幸
You are the only man who truly does.
克雷斯
Crixus.
甘尼克斯和卢戈回来了
Gannicus and Lugo return.
斯巴达克斯有话要跟你说
Spartacus would have words.
他们在一处山谷
They have laid eyes upon a valley.
发现了二十多座宅子
Twenty or more villas nestled within.
还有数不清的牛羊
Bounty of cattle and goat grazing lands.
那还等什么
Then let us fall upon them,
就让罗马人和牲畜的血
and see the blood of beasts and Romans
与今晚的月色交相辉映
mingle beneath night's moon.
破晓之时
And upon dawn's break,
我将拔营北进
I would press north.
向阿尔卑斯山进军
Towards rise of the Alps.
你想在山上安营扎寨吗
You would set up camp upon the mountains?
不
No.
我要越过山脉
I would cross them.
在山的那一边 让我们的人四散而去
And upon other side, see our people to the winds.
他这回是疯彻底了吗
Has he at last gone fucking mad?
若是一支大军 克拉苏很容易追上
Crassus pursues a single army, easily tracked.
可要是成千上万个奴隶
Thousands of slaves running free
在共和国的疆域外自由来去
beyond lands of the Republic…?
即便是他克拉苏 也没有能力
Not even he has resource enough to find so many
到国外找到那么多人
scattered across foreign soil.
我们所做的一切
All that we have done.
还有我们失去的一切
All that has been lost.
要是我们就这样跑了 将会变得毫无意义
It will stand for nothing, if we now turn and flee.
要是我们留下 克拉苏还会打过来
If we stay, Crassus will again be upon us and
让他们来
Let them come.
我们打败过他们
We have bested them before.
或许我们还能再赢一次
And perhaps we may again.
但是代价呢
But at what cost?
我们之中又会死多少人
How many more among us will fall?
多少不会舞刀弄剑的女人
How many woman, unable to raise arms?
多少呱呱坠地的孩子
Or children, new to this world?
我要让他们得到自由
I would have them free.
远离共和国渐逼渐近的阴影
Absent darkening shadow of the Republic.
那就刺穿它的心脏
Well, then let us pierce its heart,
让那阴影永远消散
and see shadow forever lifted.
克拉苏的军队会从南方压过来
Crassus' army pushes from the south.
若是向西进军 我们能在他的军团回防之前
If we were to turn west we would be at the gates of Rome
先人一步攻打罗马
before his legions could turn to defend the city.
你想直接攻打罗马
You would strike at Rome itself?
我要它瑟瑟发抖
And would see it tremble.
正如当年巴蒂塔斯家灭亡时
As the man you once were thundered
你所做的一样
when Batiatus fell.
你们先下去吧
Leave us.
你知道我所说的更有道理
You know that I hold higher ground on this.
有多少罗马人倒在我们的剑下
How many Romans have we seen to the afterlife?
共和国听到斯巴达克斯
The Republic quakes
及其奴隶大军时 就吓得发抖
at the name of Spartacus and his army of slaves.
我们不过是触动了冰山一角
We have but nipped at the ankle of the beast.
可要推翻整座大山 我…
To bare teeth at its throat, I…
如今我害怕它的报复
I now fear the reprisal.
你 携雨之使者
The Bringer of Rain?
屠影之英雄 居然会害怕
The Slayer of the Shadow of Death? Afraid?
我无所谓害怕
Not for myself, no.
但我要考虑的远远不止我个人的安危
But my concerns have grown far beyond such.
我厌倦了避而不战
I grow tired of running.
那就歇息吧
Then rest.
去陪伴妮维雅
With Naevia at your side.
不 她不想背离我们的大业
No, she does not want to turn from cause.
我也不想
Nor I.
直到我们摧毁了罗马
Until Rome falls beneath our feet.
你这是要我们走向死亡
You would have us march to our end.
我这是要大家得到自由
I would have us free.
真正的自由
Truly free.
你真以为登上了山顶
Do you really believe that Crassus will stop
克拉苏就会停止追捕你们吗
once you crest the mountains?
共和国就让我们这样悄悄地溜走吗
That the Republic will let us quietly slip away?
我们让他们见识到了自身的脆弱
We have shown them vulnerable.
我们让他们见识到哪怕是颤抖的手
We have shown them that a trembling hand
也可以捏成拳头
can become a fist.
什么奴隶必须明白自己的地位
We have challenged the idea
什么必须学会接受主人的棍棒和鞭打
that a slave must always know his place,
我们彻底改变了这一无耻的观念
accepting rod and lash because he was taught to accept it.
他们强大的共和国是我们建立的
We built their mighty Republic.
是我们用双手 用鲜血还有生命建立的
With our hands and our blood and our lives.
再来一次 我们必能让它倒下
And we can see it fall, at equal cost.
是你让我睁眼看清一切 斯巴达克斯
You opened my eyes to this, Spartacus.
不要让我闭上眼睛了
Do not ask me now to close them.
从前多么简单
It was simpler between us.
只有同仇敌忾
When the bond stood only as hate.
那些日子都过去了
Those days are sadly past.
不管有没有你
With or without you,
我都要向罗马进军
I shall march upon Rome.
带领同样渴望复仇的人得偿所愿
With those who share desire for vengeance.
我们为之奋斗的正是自由选择的权利
We have fought for the choice to forge our own path.
我不会再挡在你的面前
I will no longer stand in the way of yours.
那就破晓之时吧
At the break of dawn then.
我们分道扬镳
We shall at last part ways.
克雷斯
Crixus.
我要请求你最后一件事
There is one final thing I would ask of you.
谷地是我们的了
The valley is taken!
让我们分享胜利的果实
Let us share in the spoils of war!
并为克雷斯
And hold feast for Crixus,
以及跟随不败战神的人饯行
and those who follow the Undefeated Gaul!
天公发狂 血雨疯降
Blood rains down from an angry sky,
老屌怒胀 老屌怒胀
My cock rages on! My cock rages on!
天公发狂 血雨疯降
Blood rains down from an angry sky,
老屌怒胀 老屌怒胀
My cock rages on! My cock rages on!
天公发狂 血雨疯降
Blood rains down from an angry sky,
老屌怒胀 老屌怒胀
My cock rages on! My cock rages on!
这酒真辣喉咙
It burns throat.
好酒都是这样
As does all proper drink.
或许你该喝水
Perhaps you should hold with water
别乱了心神
and more purer thoughts.
或许你该再拿一杯来
Or perhaps you should get another.
这杯要喝完了
This one's gone empty…
早上起来脑袋疼可别怪我
Recall when head pounds upon morning
我只是遵命行事
but I but follow command.
你现在跟那小东西在一起
You are with little thing, now?
抱歉
Apologies.
我不是故意要伤你的心
I did not wish to see heart wounded.
你的烈酒还有为人
You will ruin little thing
迟早会毁了那个小东西
with drink and ways of your kind.
到头你还会到我床上来
And you again will find my bed.
不一起喝一杯
You do not share in drink?
我要保持头脑清醒
I would have clear head.
等到天亮 克雷斯就要攻打罗马了
When sun breaks, and Crixus strikes for Rome.
我和高卢人不太合得来
I have often been at cross purpose with the Gaul.
不过他走了 我还是会想他的
Yet his fucking presence shall be missed.
我就体会不到这种痛苦了
I shall not feel the sting of it.
你还是很讨厌他
You yet hate the man?
我不用想念他
I will not miss his presence…
因为我不会离开他
Because I shall not be from it.
你要离开斯巴达克斯 跟克雷斯走
You turn from Spartacus to march with Crixus?
斯巴达克斯如同我的兄长
Spartacus stands as a brother.
可惜这次我们想法不同
Yet in this we are not of like mind.
阿尔卑斯山那边的生活不适合我
There is no life for me beyond the Alps.
我既不会放羊 也不会耕地
I am no shepherd nor tiller of land.
只知道流血打仗
Blood and battle are all I have ever known.
那就这么定了
It is settled then.
明天我们跟克雷斯同去罗马
Tomorrow we move for Rome with Crixus.
听你这么说我很高兴
To hear such words lifts spirit.
但我要你和斯巴达克斯一起走
Yet I would have you take with Spartacus.
我要永远在你身边
My place is forever with you.
这次不行
Not in this.
你曾经对天发誓
You once swore the gods themselves
不会抛下我
could not wrest me from your arms.
现在就他妈的想把我甩了
And now you fucking cast me aside?
我的心只为你一人跳动
My heart will never beat for another.
如果我害死了你
Yet it would seize within chest,
我的心也就死了
if I were to drag you to your doom.
我是战士
I am a warrior.
我为你骄傲
One I am most proud of.
尽力辅佐斯巴达克斯
Set skills to aiding Spartacus,
带领他们获得真正的自由
and see those less able to true freedom.
别让我离开你
Do not ask me to turn from you.
我只要你活着
I ask only that you live.
快快乐乐地度过余生
And wrest what joy that yet may be found in the remaining days.
克雷斯
Crixus.
我有话说
I would break words.
要是劝他改主意
They will fall upon hardest stone,
那还是死心吧
if they seek to alter mind.
我不过是想和高卢英雄
I would seek to share drink.
更尽一杯酒罢了
With a man most worthy.
很少这么多愁善感啊
A sentiment not always held.
也不该这样
Nor always deserved.
彼此彼此
By either of us.
有时候他们都认为我冷酷无情
I've been known to be contrary, upon occasion.
这是我胜过你的诸多优点之一
A talent among many that I best you in.
我们还没有杀了对方 真是奇迹
It is a wonder. We have not yet killed each other.
真希望回到过去
Would that we could reverse the years,
改变我们的处境
towards better footing.
我看不出有什么差别
I would not see it different.
我们完成了不可能之事
We have done the impossible.
推翻巴蒂塔斯家族
Seen the House of Batiatus to ruin.
捣毁卡普亚竞技场
Laid waste to the arena of Capua.
打倒葛雷博以及随后而来的罗马军队
Defeated Glaber and all of the Roman hordes who followed.
让死了的心重新跳动
Restored heart torn from chest.
如果你我所爱之人没被夺走
If you and I had taken to loving arms,
那么命运会指引我们走上平淡的人生
fate may have led us on a less glorious path.
巴蒂塔斯曾经警告我
Batiatus once warned me
人要顺天意而行
that a man must accept his fate
否则必为命运所毁
or will be destroyed by it.
那混账跟谁都这么说
The fucking cunt said that to everyone.
祝你得偿所愿
I pray that yours holds all you desire.
愿今生我们能够再度聚首
And that one day we can greet each other again in this life.
血债血偿
Roman blood!
伤口疼吗
Does it cause pain?
伤口都是可以痊愈的
All wounds heal upon a day.
就怕梅泰勒斯的伤口
Though I fear injury delivered to Metellus
只会腐烂生疮
may never cease to fester.
梅泰勒斯有生之年
For all his remaining days,
都会害怕马科斯•克拉苏这个名字
Metellus will fear the name Marcus Crassus.
地位更低的人 更要好好地教训
Times those beneath us must be struck severest blow.
要他们知道天高地厚
To truly grasp how we tower above them.
永远没胆子背叛我们
And to ensure they never betray us.
梅泰勒斯这回学乖了
A lesson well learned by Metellus.
如果克芮得到过同样的教训…
Perhaps if Kore had been given similar instruction
别提她的名字
Do not form sound of her name.
抱歉
Apologies.
她伤您这么深 我很难过
It tears heart to know how deeply she wounded you.
我什么都给她了
I gave all that I could.
全然不顾她奴隶的身份
Treated her as if word of slave held no meaning.
为什么她还是不顾一切地离开我
Why would she risk all to fly from loving arms?
这都怪我
I hold myself to blame.
这件事怎能怪到你头上
What did your hands do to cause such a thing?
因为我不作为
It is what they did not.
我就知道恺撒不可信
I knew Caesar to be untrustworthy.
如果我看紧了他
If I had laid closer eye upon him,
他就不能带她到山上去
he would not have been able to see her to the ridge…
她也就没机会逃走了
and allowed opportunity of escape.
恺撒行事放荡不羁
Caesar is of wild mind.
但我不认为他知道她的想法
Yet I do not believe he knew her thoughts in this.
我知道权力越大责任越大
And I believe that great power is accompanied
担子更沉 父亲
by many burdens, father.
要分清谁是最值得信赖的人
Knowing whom to trust paramount among them.
你说得很好
Wisdom well received.
你确定吗
You are certain of this?
我心里左右矛盾了很久
I have for heavy span been pulled in opposing direction.
我知道
A thing I have noted.
谢谢你一直支持我
Gratitude for standing by my words,
虽然你并不赞同我的观点
even when you did not believe in them.
我信的是你这个人
I believed in the man.
永远都信
And always shall.
艾力冈
Agron.
希望你能得到想要的
I hope you find what you seek.
你经历了这么多艰难困苦 希望你得到慰藉
And you some measure of comfort, despite all that has happened.
你是最应该得到慰藉的人 兄弟
No one is more deserving of it, brother.
克芮在哪儿
Where is Kore?
睡得正香呢
Wrapped in arms of relieved slumber.
她感到很庆幸 自己还活着
And filled with gratitude that she yet draws breath.
这是你的功劳
A kindness moved by your tongue.
没想到你会对一个奴隶这么好心
One I did not expect to make sound towards life of a slave.
我还是女主人时
I mistreated none within my house,
可从不苛待奴隶
when I was yet called domina.
但你仍将他们视为物品
Yet you held them as possessions.
随意买卖交易
Things to be bought and traded.
克拉苏待我也是一样 难道你忘记了
As I was by Crassus himself, or have you forgotten…
你这才多长时间
You have suffered but briefest moment
很多人一辈子深陷苦海
of that which so many have only ever known.
你是要比比谁的伤痛更深吗
You desire to compare wounds?
那就说说看 然后评判一番
Let us weigh them, and judge balance.
看来你的伤已经痊愈了
Your wounds must be all but healed.
又变成原来那个难缠的女人了
You return to difficult woman of old.
天性难改
We cannot turn from truest nature.
的确
No.
天性难改
We cannot.
去参加宴会吧
Rejoin celebration.
明早就要长途跋涉了
Hard journey awaits at dawn's break.
酒已经喝够了
I have had my fill of wine.
只需要有人陪
And company less desired…
你还是罗马人
You yet stand Roman.
我永远不能与你交心
A thing I can never hold to heart.
今晚我要的不是你的心
It is not your heart I'm after this night…
当年那个在竞技场上目瞪口呆
It seems but yesterday you stood as opened-mouthed Gaul,
急于证明实力的高卢人 仿佛就在昨天
anxious to prove yourself in the arena.
如今有数千人自愿追随你
Now thousands gladly follow you,
去攻打罗马了
lay assault upon Rome itself.
要是你也能加入我们的行列
I would hold it as a blessing from Jupiter himself,
那就真是诸神眷顾了
if you would join with us.
我走的是另一条路
My journey leads toward other path.
让男人放下屠刀
There is no greater cause,
无疑是最伟大的功业
to turn a man from battle.
准备好了吗
Do we stand ready?
等你下令 我们就启程去罗马
Upon your command, we move for Rome.
我仍然怀疑你的选择
A decision I yet hold in grievous doubt.
但要是我信仰诸神
Yet if I believed in the gods,
我必定虔诚祈求 是我想错了
I would split heavens in prayer that I was mistaken.
而我要尽我所能 证明你是傻瓜
And I would give my all to prove you yet the fool.
带上粮草
Shoulder supplies!
我们北上阿尔卑斯
We move north for the mountains!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus…
当我们还是巴蒂塔斯的角斗士时
When we were yet of Batiatus' ludus,
我说过我们有可能成为兄弟
I spoke of how we may have been as brothers,
等到下辈子
in another life.
而非今生
Yet not in this one.
是我错了
Know that I was wrong.
今生我永远当你是兄弟
And will always hold you as such.
我也是
As I will hold you.
斯巴达克斯兵分两路了吗
Spartacus divides his forces?
大部队将北上阿尔卑斯山
The larger sum striking north towards the mountains.
女人和孩子大大拖慢了他们的脚步
Their numbers weighted by women and children.
剩下的呢
The remainder?
他们往哪边走
What course do they take?
西进
West.
去罗马吗
Towards Rome?
您要我们阻截哪一路
What path would you have us follow?
只有一条路可行
There is but one.
我们必须保卫罗马
The city must be defended.
沿路自有人阻截他们
Others will give resistance upon way.
艾瑞斯的军团在城门外防守
And Arrius and his legion hold position beyond its gates.
单凭一个军团也只能拦截斯巴达克斯一时
A single legion will give Spartacus briefest pause.
看情况 领军西进的并非斯巴达克斯
Spartacus does not command western forces, upon sighting of exodus.
是他的高卢走狗带队
His pet Gaul leads assault.
克雷斯吗
Crixus?
此人战力与他相当 而且更加嗜血
A man of equal skill and deadlier passion.
毕竟不是该死的携雨之使者
Not the Bringer of Fucking Rain.
我们不能置罗马于不顾
We cannot leave Rome undefended.
艾瑞斯可以拖住克雷斯
Arrius will slow Crixus' advance,
足够我们先去打击较弱的斯巴达克斯
granting needed time to set upon Spartacus and weakened numbers.
我们必须攻其弱点
We must press advantage.
听这孩子的话 罗马就危险了
Follow advice of this child, and Rome herself may fall.
罗马一旦被攻陷 我们就全完了
And with her everything we have fucking reached for.
我受够了你这样
I have had fill of you questioning
我说什么你反驳什么
every word that falls from my tongue.
那你就少胡扯
Then break them with more fucking sense.
我们不能丢下罗马不管
We cannot turn from Rome.
我们怎么行动由我父亲决定
We shall turn in whatever direction my father decides.
那就献上良策
Then aid him in proper choice.
而不是顺水推舟 溜须拍马
Not one you believe he seeks to hear.
我说的都是我自己的想法
I follow my own desires.
强奸克芮也是你自己的想法吗
As you did when you forced yourself upon Kore,
就在你父亲夺回希留爱沙的那晚
the night your father reclaimed Sinuessa?
我警告过你 要想人不知除非己莫为
I warned you that your deed would fall to discovery.
为了整我 你开始编故事了吗
You would fabricate lies now, to see me lessened…
别装了 小子
The game is over, boy.
那个妓女坎莎拉说她看到你从克芮帐篷里出来
The whore Canthara tells of how she saw you come from Kore's tent.
发现她备受欺凌
Of finding her roughly used.
她被迫答应对当晚看到的事
She was made to promise never to reveal
永远闭口不谈
what her eyes laid upon.
但我这张嘴皮子厉害着呢
But I can be very, very persuasive.
不过一个为钱卖身的女人
You risk all on the tale of a woman
她的故事你也押宝吗
who swallows cock for coin?
过去比这更不靠谱的赌注
I have made more uncertain wagers,
我也不是没赌过
in years past.
我这不活得好好的
And yet here I stand.
那你怎么不去跟他告状
Then why have you not yet told him?
得知心爱的奴隶背叛 他已经承受不住了
He has been pushed to brink of madness by imagined betrayal.
我不想再拿残酷的事实去刺激他
I would not see him forced over precipice by truth
让他不堪重负
of harsher realities.
那你要我怎么做
What would you have of me?
我早就说过了
What you have already been asked.
你父亲听你的意见
You have your father's ear.
让他恢复理智
Bring him to reason,
我命令你怎么说 你就…
breaking words as I command them…
我才不听你的命令
I do not take command from you!
你最好接受我的提议 小子
You should have accepted offer, boy.
你父亲差点让你在十一抽杀中丧命
Your father nearly saw you to end in decimation.
如果他得知了你的所作所为
Perhaps he shall see fate to completion
那就不会手下留情…
when he hears what you have done
抓住他
Seize him!
起来
Get up!
再也不许你对我出手
You shall never lay hands upon me again.
不许再鬼话连篇
Nor whisper lies against me.
你不能杀我
You cannot take my life
你没办法偷偷摸摸弄走我的尸体
and see my body from encampment absent notice.
老子可是盖乌斯•恺撒
I am Julius Fucking Caesar
把他按住
Hold him against table.
你跟梅泰勒斯一个德行
You are of same cloth as Metellus.
非要好好教训你一番
And must be taught severest lesson
才知道天高地厚
in who towers above you…
你胆敢泄漏一个字
Speak of what you know to anyone…
我就要众人皆知 伟大的恺撒
and I shall spin tale of the mighty Caesar…
跟娘们一样被爆菊
taken like a woman…
今天属于我们
The day is ours.
哪天不是呢
When is it fucking not?!
准备进军
Prepare to march.
还有一仗便大功告成
There is one battle yet remaining.
（罗马）
罗马 终于近在咫尺了
Rome at last lies within our grasp!
我们前方只有蠢货艾瑞斯
One last legion led by the fool Arrius
以及他率领的军团了
is all that stands between us…
我们的胜利将成为传奇
and a victory that shall become legend!
很久以前 当我还是
A lifetime ago when I yet stood beneath the roof
巴蒂塔斯家的奴隶时
of the House of Batiatus…
我的教练奥诺玛默斯
my doctore Oenomaus demanded answer
问那些打算在竞技场上
from those recruits who sought glory
追求荣誉的新人
upon the sands of the arena.
你们脚下是什么
"What lies beneath your feet?!"
是圣地
Sacred ground!
浸满了血泪的土地
Watered with tears of blood!
今天
And this day…
轮到罗马人的血泪浸染大地了
it shall be Rome who sheds them!
可以开始了吗
Shall we begin?!
Shall we begin?!!!
火球准备
Bring fire forth.
停
Halt!
盾牌
Shields!
举起盾牌防御
Raise your fucking shields!
后方没有什么危险
Rear position stands absent threat.
但愿一直如此
Pray it remains so.
少了克雷斯和跟他走的人
Our numbers stand ill match absent Crixus
要是克拉苏打过来
and those who follow him,
我们完全不是对手
if Crassus were to set upon us.
艾瑞斯败了
Arrius has fallen!
你就是天神下凡
You stand as a fucking god.
罗马因你而颤抖
With Rome trembling before you.
正如斯巴达克斯发过的誓
As Spartacus once promised.
汇报
Give report.
全军待命 统帅
The men stand ready, Imperator.
恺撒
Caesar.
你今天怎么沦落至此
How have you come to be so rudely handled?
我与人争执 有失体面
I found myself in shameful altercation.
再也不能这样了
It shall not happen again.
为什么不骑马
And reason you not astride horse?
我命令他徒步冲锋 统帅
I gave command for him to lead charge upon foot, Imperator.
这样更能激励普通士兵的士气
To rally the common men that hold him in such high regard.
我们来结束这一切
Let us see this to proper end,
再去追击斯巴达克斯
and return to pursuit of Spartacus.
他们人多势众
They will attempt to overrun position!
就让他们自以为是吧
Let them think they have succeeded,
我们从两翼包抄击败他们
and fall upon them from our flanks!
你是不败的高卢人
You are the undefeated Gaul.
让他们知道这个名号实至名归
Let us show them how such name was earned.
吹号
Sound horns!
拿好长矛和利剑
Bring spear and sword to bear!
杀他个片甲不留
And fall upon them all.
要这帮杂碎统统归西
Send them to the fucking afterlife!
父亲
Father!
撤退 撤回高地
Fall back and re-form upon higher advantage!
尝尝老子的厉害
Drink my fucking piss,
罗马狗
you Roman cunts
恺撒
Caesar!
敌方东翼已溃败
Their eastern flank has been broken!
前进
Advance!
他们人数太多了
There are too many.
如果克拉苏死了 我们还是能赢
If Crassus falls, we may yet seize fucking day!
克雷斯
Crixus!
不
No!
我不会让你这么容易就死了 盖乌斯
I would not have you so easily leave from this world, Gaius.
克雷斯
Crixus!
让那个婊子闭嘴
Silence that fucking bitch.
住手
Hold!
这就是想打垮罗马的高卢人
This is the Gaul that would seek the fall of Rome?
还有他的臭婊子
And his fucking woman.
败在我手下
Defeated by my hand.
拿回你的剑
Retrieve your sword.
早就该回到主人手里了
It has been too long from proper hands.
这人还没死
The man yet lives.
我要钉死他
I shall see him crucified
不
No.
我要借此机会给斯巴达克斯送个信
I would use opportunity to send message to Spartacus.
让他知道败得有多惨
So that he may know the depths of his failure.
而他注定只能是这样的下场
And what fate I shall see him to as well.
砍下他的头
Take his head.